all right welcome to uh
mse 2044 fundamentals of materials
engineering i'm going to try and uh
answer a bunch of your questions about
how
class is going to work in this
asynchronous and synchronous online
environment
so our class has both the uh
synchronous um and asynchronous
components so the main part of the class
on tuesdays and thursdays
meaning that's what i'm going to try and
make sure i post your lectures
that part of the class is asynchronous
and
the friday lecture from 125 to 215
is actually a synchronous so make sure
you get that on your
on your schedules that's going to be the
communications program
which is integrated throughout this
entire course
so we'll have a workshop on friday and
we'll talk more about the
communications program and the research
paper that
you all are going to write so let's
first
take a look at the canvas site so we can
kind of see what's
going on there because we do have
several different
i guess sites and software that that you
all be interacting with
through this course so the main part of
the site
you can see here in canvas we'll have
the
policy guide just make sure you look
through that the
homework submission guide and also this
video lectures this is a new link so if
you
have already looked at the canvas site
you may not have noticed this one
but what i'm going to be doing is
placing
this is a this is one of your pages in
your page view
i'm going to continue to update
see if this opens for us
all right well why that's working what
i'm going to do is i'm going to
upload the video lectures and i'm going
to keep
on this page a kind of running table of
contents for you
so your video lectures will just get
embedded directly into
the page views in canvas so you can see
them
relatively easily i'm not sure what it's
doing right now
um there is a
media tool in canvas and if you were to
look there you'd see there's
a bunch of video files unfortunately
that tool is not very good
at organizing things so when i tried to
pull a lot of that over it got
completely disorganized so
just ignore that i mean i'm going to try
and just keep
up to date this particular pages table
of contents
okay so here it is finally it's come up
for me
you can see there's not a lot there
right now there's just this chapter one
and two playlist
and then after i finish this video i'm
going to put that on here as an
introduction to the class you'll see
that
but if we were to go to this chapter one
and two playlists this will just pull up
another page file that's in your system
and then on here what we're going to see
is the
chapter 1 lecture and the chapter 2
lecture
here they come so there's our chapter 2
and you can always make this full screen
if you like
and then the chapter one hopefully
eventually come up here
okay so there it is there's chapter one
so you've got these two
that'll get you started uh for this week
and then i'll continue to add these as
we as we move on i think this will be a
better way to organize
things you can always go to the
view all pages if you want to see what's
kind of going on behind the scenes
and i know canvas has been been behaving
really slow today
i think that's part of the problem here
uh hopefully that'll get better
as the semester gets gets going
okay so this brings up all of the pages
that we've got going on you can see here
this is the
chapter one and two playlists then i'll
continue to add those
um but you don't have to worry about it
it's all here in the
video lectures file folder that's
basically the big
table of contents that i was just
showing you
previously
so there it is okay so that's where the
video lectures will show up um let's see
let's take a look
at the um at some of the announcements
because i'm getting a lot of different
kinds of questions
that um lead me to believe that
you all aren't quite reading all of the
announcements and i know that they're
long and
you're probably skimming through them
but a lot of your questions are actually
answered in there
although maybe i've written in a
confusing way so let's let's go ahead
and
take a look at those announcements for
you
okay so we've got three announcements so
far in the class
let's go ahead and we'll take a look
quickly well i'll say the first one
i sent pretty early on before the
semester actually started
this one's just giving you some
information on the textbook and
the requirement for using the
perusal.com site so hopefully
many of you i know at least well half so
actually not
too many of you i've already signed up
for the perusal you do need to get the
e-text
um that's in perusal that's where you're
going to be
annotating and commenting and
interacting with me and with the
other fellow students through the
perusal site i'll talk about that a
little bit more in a second
um and that is graded so i know that's
always the uh
motivation that gets you working on some
of these things
so over the grade breakdown in just a
second
all right so let's take a look at the
assignments uh clarification here
okay so here it is looking at the
assignments so
again all of your assignment due dates
will be in one place
in canvas so even though you have
assignments in different places
the canvas will actually show you the
due dates for all of them
and which assignments are due and so
i'll take a look at that
also with you in just a second but for
this chapter one and two for example
there are several components to your
your homework that you can all find
under assignments
you can also find it under syllabus so
i'll show you that as well
and you can find it under calendar
okay so right now there's
for your first assignment you're going
to have
a canvas discussion and a canvas poll
these are very quick and this should not
take you
a lot of time at all it's just kind of
for fun and
talking about whether you prefer glass
cans
or plastic bottles for drinking soda so
this is technically done through a quiz
don't worry this is not again not a big
deal just asking for your preference you
can't get it wrong
all right the canvas discussion is where
you can talk about why you made your
preference and this will link you
automatically to the poll
okay so that's here under discussions
the um they're also callister your
textbook
there are problems that will be doing
there each
week so maybe sometimes more than one
homework each week depending on how many
chapters we go through
and in the perusal software
i mark all of your homework at the end
of those chapters
actually i guess in the e-text it's at
the beginning of the chapters
but i will mark highlight all of the
ones you need to do
and i will hashtag them with homework so
that in perusal
you can easily see where they are okay
now those homework problems are workout
problems
and once you work those problems out you
can turn those into a pdf file
and you will upload them in canvas okay
so canvas is actually where
where that goes the everything goes into
canvas
except for your reading assignment so
the reading assignments
are listed in perusal i'll have a spot
here in canvas that just lists them so
that
you have a due date and a reminder that
that you have reading
but you don't need to turn anything in
in canvas
okay so perusal will grade your reading
assignments
and your reading assignments consist
of reading through the text and
highlighting
annotating answering interacting with
other students and i'm going to go
through a little bit of that
and perusal is going to grade you
automatically so it's got a little bit
of
some artificial intelligence going on a
little bit there
and i'll talk again about that in just a
second
the other place problems that we may
have
and we do in this first set is you're
going to have what's called ces
edupack problems so ces edupac is
a software for material selection that
you'll use in other courses throughout
our curricula
it allows you to look up all sorts of
material properties
so i will have supplemental problems
that will
allow you to use that software so make
sure you go to the
student software i believe that's online
now
and you can just download the ces
edupack
so there is a cost for that i believe
it's about 25 bucks
okay all right so i know that's a lot of
different places and that's why
if you go to the assignments link let me
just
click over there right now
okay so here we are in the assignments
link
you're seeing my view so there's a lot
more on here than what you'll see
don't worry about all the gray stuff
none of that will show up
it's only the green here that's going to
show up in
in your view and that's all you have to
worry about so perusal
okay there'll always be a reminder here
your chapter one and two reading that's
due
it's due august 28th that's friday
okay perusal this reading assignments
are going to count as ten percent of
your grade
okay and it's listed here for you and
as periodically as we move through the
course and certainly by the end
i will take the grades from perusal and
then i will
substitute them directly in here so they
end up showing
up in your gradebook all right but
you'll be able to see your perusal
grades
after the assignments are done and you
get graded for that
all right the homework
so this could be a variety of things
this is the
in this first part this is the beverage
container
uh and the poll you know these aren't
going to count
for much it's just participation it's
your
callister workout problems and your ces
edupack software problems so that's all
that's going on right now
and you can see again the due dates um
august 25th that's today
by midnight so do those and then august
31st which is monday for your
other two sets of problems uh but
they're all listed here
so even if your homework is up in
perusal it's going to show up here
as a due date all right
so for your callister problems
and your ces edupack problems you would
just click on these links here
and it'll give you the ability to upload
your pdf file once you've got that that
finished
the cs edupack problems a lot of times
it's just going to ask you to look up a
record
right now anyway and find out a certain
property
so all you have to do is is do that in
the software then just take a small
screen clip of the spot in your
software that shows the value that we
were looking for and just paste that
into
maybe pdf annotator or word and then
save that as a pdf file
but you just want to take a screenshot
of the results you don't have to
document every step you went through
for the edupack problems here okay but
both of these will get turned in
all right so don't worry about all the
rest of the stuff we've got a lot to
look forward to here
um so this you know this may get a
little bit confusing you know perhaps to
sort through so if you do go to the
syllabus
and you scroll down
apparently it gets messed up there if
you scroll down to
the bottom then this is just going to be
a summary list of everything that's due
okay so everything that right now is is
there
all right so some of these actually
won't show up in your view because
these are not actually i should go into
the
student view let me show you from the
student view because this is
a bit confusing
okay let's try that again uh student
view
there we go much better so right now
when you go to your student view you're
going to see the
the discussion and the poll
your reading assignment and your calstr
and ces problems
okay so they're just listed here in date
order so
you can't go wrong taking a look at the
summary
of what's coming up okay if you take a
look at the
let's see the ces edupack problems
if we were to take a look at that you'll
see it'll walk you through exactly what
you need to do with that software and
i'm going to put up a short video
um for thursday
that'll walk you through ces we'll take
a look at that program so
you can just wait don't worry about this
homework until after we do that
all right let's see what else do we got
um
all right that so let's go um let's see
look calendars
so that's the additional place
so your courses this should be for all
of your canvas courses
um should be here and you can color code
them as you like
but again you'll see now on a calendar
the due dates of your different
assignments and you can
click on these directly if you want so
that's another place to look to help
organize you a little bit
all right so i think that is all of the
canvas stuff so let us jump
over to perusal
all right so in perusal
come over here to the course home
assignments link up here this is where
your assignments are going to be
these are your reading assignments so
right now we just have this
chapter one and two reading assignment
okay
and what you're going to do if you open
that assignment and you'll see i've
already commented some things in here
i'll wait for that to load just a second
all right so here's the textbook
and you're reading and
i'll usually go through a lot of these
chapters beforehand
and as you're reading them and i will
comment
on your comments this is a great place
to put questions
as you're reading through if you're
having trouble with anything
this is the great place to put your
questions
if you start your homeworks this is a
good reason not to start them at the
last minute
but if you start your homeworks actually
you don't have any in chapter one let me
go to
chapter two here
all right here's chapter two and if you
start looking through these
you will find
here we go that your homeworks are
highlighted
okay so i highlight these and this is
just a
comment um many times it'll just be the
problem number
and i'll hashtag it homework so you
don't miss it
um this one has a comment you know make
sure you show your work
for credit here there's another one
like this one it's going to re tell you
make sure your plot is computer
generated no hand plots i'm not going to
accept any hand plots you get no credit
okay so i will also put up a short video
on
using excel to make plots of functions
so that
that will help you out with this problem
all right
so that's where your homeworks will be
but this is a great place if you're
running into trouble
let's say you are trying to plot this
and you're having some kind of an issue
with excel
this is the place to go ahead and you
know highlight where you're having your
problem and enter your
question okay and then other students
can help feel free to help i would
rather you
be the ones to help each other i
hopefully i'll only come in to help if
either a no one is or b the discussion
uh gets off track and and you're all
confusing each other more but generally
you answer questions
many times better than i do so please
help each other
and helping each other goes right into
your
grading goes right into the perusal
grade okay keeps track of all sorts of
things
and some of those things are
responding to other students questions
so
so use this again to interact with each
other and
interacting with me if you
click on the this one here this will
show you
all of the comments that are currently
here called conversations
you can use this to just show your own
comments
and you can look at the other options
here but
i'll usually leave it on all comments
you can see the homeworks that are kind
of hashtagged
so far okay and then as we move
out of this section into the next
sections
down here this will start to move
into your text that's summary pages take
a look at those
very useful
resources all right finally i think
we're getting to the text part
most likely since it's taken a second
there we go so
when you get into the text part then
you'll find
conversations from myself and from other
students so
um and many times i'll put in here like
in chapter one i'll say just go ahead
and skim
or as we go on i'll say skip this uh
particular section you don't need to
worry about this so
i will comment throughout that way and i
might make some clarifying comments
as you can look through you'll see on
the bond energy stuff
i put those in there to try and clarify
some
typical problems that come up
all right so again make sure that you
are commenting on each other's
and commenting on the text
if you uh if you like to read hard
copies um
you can get some hard copies you can get
an old edition
pretty cheap feel free to do that
what you're going to want to do though
is use this perusal as your way of
interacting with the class
and this is where you're going to get
graded so you can put in
questions that you have when you're
doing your own reading you could
highlight
and you know make a comment about things
that you think are important
or you can read through other students
comments and
comment to those you can upvote you can
ask
me questions so all sorts of ways of
interacting with the text that'll all go
into your grade
all right the hashtags over here on the
bottom left so again if here is the
easiest way to get your homework
assignments
instead of scrolling through just hit
hashtag homework
and as i keep going through all your
chapters it all show up here but there's
your
homeworks for chapter two
all right you can also look under
hashtag instructor
uh everything that i type into
perusal i will hashtag with instructor
so that's
one place you can see that and
if it's particularly a clarifying
question i might
hashtag it with a clarification so those
are just sometimes helpful hints
for you and if it's a
section that you can just skim i'll put
a hashtag skim on it
okay so you can take a look at those
so use those hashtags and you can use
the hashtags in
your own comments so feel free to
hashtag if you want
you can i guess use the at and
[Music]
direct things to one of your fellow
students and you can use it to direct
stuff to me that you want to make sure
that i that i see
once we start getting a lot of comments
going on on here
all right so that's
your assignments there also be a library
right
now it just has your course text in it
but i will put in here the pdf versions
um of the slides that go along with your
lecture
video lectures so feel free to comment
uh
on the slides if you have questions
there and
i or other students can also address
those
there as well all right
so that is perusal again it's to
try and keep up the interaction uh
between you
and me um on this online environment
and so please take advantage of it and
um
you know i look forward to to seeing all
of your
comments and and commenting with to you
all
okay so let's go ahead and we'll jump
back over to um
canvas and just want to
point out the instructor policy guide so
you can see what my grading scale looks
like
and the waiting i've got homework at 10
perusal at 10.
45 for your exams there's three of those
you have a research paper due and that's
we'll talk about on friday
and you have a final exam so this is the
waiting and hopefully that adds to 100.
read through the honor system stuff all
the standard
sorts of things related to the the honor
system
so you go ahead and do that since this
is completely online course
we don't have to worry about the covid
and social distancing and
mask wearing so i won't talk about
all of that in these these interesting
times
all right so that's the instructor's
policy guide
okay if we jump over to the
announcements again
it's the assignment clarification i just
wanted to point out
the many of the things i was telling you
about perusal
is written at the bottom there and so
these are all the sorts of things that
are graded
in perusal for your grades
okay so starting reading
early and looking through the
the textbook throughout the week or
whenever this assignment is is due
rather than waiting to the last minute
is actually taken
up into your account into your grade so
if you're trying to cram all your
reading and your
comments in on the last day the hour
before it's due
it will penalize you okay so
again the idea is to interact and you
can't interact with each other
if you're doing it at the last minute
okay and so
we need to spread out your reading and
your commenting
in working on the class daily and that
will help
with your grade so break your reading
into chunks
and you know comment with your fellow
classmates
answering questions from others accounts
you asking questions that elicit
comments or responses from other
students help
also your grade as well as theirs for
answering
up voting there's you know some small
amount for upvoting so don't go crazy up
voting everything just
trying to pick up your grade but but do
upload things that are that are
important all right
um if you start to feel like you're not
finding
things to comment on because it seems
like everyone has commented then
you might not be reading early enough so
again get in there and and get your
reading done
all right well i think that is
everything i hope um i'm sure i missed
some stuff so feel free to uh
to email me um or to post questions
where appropriate in perusal and i can
try and help you
i think what 26 minutes that this video
is a little bit longer
i will generally try and keep all of the
videos
you know hopefully it's sort of the 10
maybe 15 at the most
minutes and so in the chapters i'll try
and
make the videos on topical so there
might be
three or four videos in a chapter but
i'll make them
specific to specific topics in that
chapter that
typically students have a difficult time
with
okay well again i look forward to
interacting with you all
i know i can't do it face to face we we
could have some zoom meetings
if you want for office hours or
something like that we can set those up
one-on-one
i can do that as a class so we can see
how things go
or we can just interact through the
perusal i really do enjoy
uh reading your comments and
interacting with you that way so
all right well enjoy the semester uh
stay safe and
get to work