all right let's go ahead and do a quick
uh look at the gronta edupak
2020 while we load up here
all right so first thing we're going to
do is again select our database
i want to look at the advanced utility
and plotting
equations and in particular we're going
to be looking at this
second ces assignment where we want to
plot a bar chart
so let me go ahead and select the
elements for this one
going to try and fit our
ces in here all right so we're going to
go ahead and we select the elements
we're going to go ahead and
select chart like we've done before
and we're going to select here from the
elements so that's
that's all that we want we're going to
go ahead and do the chart index again
and and this is the same thing you would
do even if it wasn't the elements if it
was like a level one or something like
that
but in your particular homework problem
you're going to be needing to use the
elements database
so the next thing you want to do for a
bar
chart is to define the y-axis only
that's referred to as a bar chart in the
edupack software
and the x-axis will just be
something like element type it'll handle
that by
itself if you were to plot the
define the x-axis and the y-axis in
terms of properties you end up with
what's called a bubble chart
and that's what you've done before so
let's go ahead and do the bar
chart now if we're going to do an
equation
rather than just selecting one property
then we need to go into the advanced
okay then here we can we can write an
equation
so i'm not going to do the one that you
have for homework but let's say
that we wanted to take a look at let's
go do look at mechanical properties
so let's say that we wanted to look at
something like
1 minus so i'm just typing that in
okay but when i get to a property i have
to put it in
through an insert command so i need to
go to poisson's ratio for example if i
wanted that
and i have to say insert okay
then i can go ahead and type and close
my parentheses
i can't type these in i need to use the
insert command to get them right
so so far i've got one minus poisson's
ratio
and then maybe i want to divide that by
something like the
bulk modulus so again i'll do bulk
modulus
and then i'll say insert okay if for
some reason
i'm going to go back here to the
beginning i wanted to multiply the
the whole thing or the top here by
something like pi
then what i would do is go to my
constants
okay and then i would find pi
and i would insert it okay and again i'm
going to need the
multiply sign so i've got pi times 1
minus the poissons ratio divided by the
bulk modulus
okay this doesn't really make any sense
but that's that's just what we're going
to plot here just for fun
if you're doing something like an
exponential then you would go ahead and
use this
base of natural logarithm you'd insert
that
and then you can use the carrot here for
the
for the power okay just like you do in
excel
if you need the gas constant then you
can see the gas constant here
in joules per mole says degrees c
joules per mole kelvin this is the same
as
uh per kelvin the difference in
degree c and difference in kelvin are
the same
so that would be our gas constant or we
could do
the boltzmann's constant just depending
on on our units of our problem but
that's where you find all this stuff
is in your constants and parameters
all right so let's just go ahead and see
what we get
we'll go ahead and say insert
i should say just offhand unlike excel
there's no equal sign out front okay
we're just writing the equation in
all right so go ahead and say insert
whoops
i didn't want to insert sorry i wanted
to say okay
put that back so again pi times one
minus poisson so now i just say okay
and it titles my axis
according to the equation i just said
and then i'll just go ahead and say
ok again if i want to change the
axes i could certainly do linear versus
logarithmic or
or set min max but i'll say ok
and it gives me a bar chart so the
reason it's you can see it's called a
bar is because
it will give these little bars
for every element okay and it's not
labeling the elements on this axis but
this would be your
element axis each one of these
corresponds to an element
but since there's some standard
deviation
in the properties like a modulus and the
poisson ratio
that results in a little standard
deviation in
the value here that we calculate and
that's why there's a bar
it represents the range of values for
that particular element
and then again you can come over here
and you could click on one of these or
just
hover and you could see what elements
are what okay and you can always click
on one
if you wanted to do something like that
and label it so there's aluminum
the other thing you can do if you were
looking for something specific
is you might not want to have to hover
over every one of these to try and find
it so
let's say we wanted to do iron
iron here we go what i can do is right
click on iron
and then i can say
highlight or i could do label
so let me just do highlight first so you
can see here the highlighted
it blinks kind of lets me know that that
there it is
and in this case it also labeled it
okay so if i want to do lead
again i could just say label and that
would do the same thing
puts a label on it i can see where that
is
all right so that's how we could do that
all right
i guess that's it for now