all right with this video i'd like to go
ahead and just introduce you to the
discipline
of material science and engineering so
we'll just start off with the definition
the goal of materials science and
engineering this enabled scientist and
engineer
to design select and use materials
for specific applications and to develop
new materials for future applications
all right a good overview of some
materials research that's going on and
just to give you a flavor
the kinds of things that materials
science
departments do i just point you to this
nova site
they've got a great series called making
stuff and it goes through a lot of
interesting
projects so i'll just leave that to you
i've sent you out a poll and a
discussion
assignment on this particular question
of whether you
enjoy the plastic bottle the glass
bottle or the aluminum can for your
favorite beverage
and why you chose what you did and we
will take a look at that in another
short video
once i get your results and we'll talk a
little bit about the idea of properties
performance and take a look at some of
the responses that
that you all make
right in material science and
engineering we'd like to talk about this
materials tetrahedron and it kind of
shows the
core of what we teach and how we
approach
engineering so the main idea is that
material science and engineers are
interested not only in the
properties or performance of a material
but we're very interested in how the
structure of a material can affect the
properties
and in ways by which we can process the
material in order to affect the
structure
and so when we know these linkages then
we're able to tailor
properties and to tailor a material for
a given performance
by undergoing a processing method
that alters the structure that gives us
the properties that we want
a combination of properties that results
in the performance
also talk about the characterization
methods we will use those in order to
measure for example structure
or to measure properties so maybe the
elastic modulus for example an attention
test
we like to think of things in terms of
this tetrahedron
and we will spend a lot of time in this
class
up front we'll be talking about
structure and then we'll be talking a
lot about properties
and their measurements or
characterization especially as
we move into chapter six and we get into
mechanical behavior
and then in the later chapters we will
touch more on the processing methods
okay just as one uh very quick example
of
optical properties this is a
this is a aluminum sorry alumina
right aluminum oxide and we have it in
several
forms we have this here as a single
crystal
we have it in a poly crystal
oops poly crystal and we have one that
is both polycrystalline
and porous
and we'll learn about what a single
crystal is in a poly crystal
as we move on through the course but
these are different
microstructures in the material and
the resultant is in the property of
optical
you have either transparent translucent
or opaque
and so the most expensive one is the
first one
single crystal but that doesn't mean
that the other two
are defective materials that are
not useful in fact they're very useful
for certain applications
so the more porosity we have in
something we lower the density
we also improve the thermal insulation
capabilities
for example
so when we say structure of a material
we could mean
many different levels at the very basic
level which is what we'll touch on
first is the atomic structure
by atomic structure what we're
interested in is the
bonding between atoms and so you'll read
about that
in chapter two and then we move up from
there and we start looking at the
arrangement
of the atoms into a crystal
and this is the atomic arrangement level
we'll do that chapter three
and then microstructure we'll talk a lot
about through most of the chapters in
the text
there we're talking about
polycrystalline samples
how the grains are arranged or we'll see
later in chapter 9 we'll talk about
different phases of compositions
throughout a material
the macrostructure will leave out
really of this course mostly we may
touch on this idea of sharp corners
but we want to hold up the macro
structure
so what do we mean by a material
property
right so material property needs to be
independent
of the size and shape of the material so
the idea is that we want it to depend on
the material itself
not on its geometry so for example um if
we were simply apply a stimulus to a
material
so for example maybe a force or stress
and we will see the material response by
deforming
our strain the property that relates the
two
experimentally will be the stiffness
and in terms of the stress strain we're
talking about the elastic modulus or
young's modulus
if you've heard of that especially if
you're from mechanical engineering
you've probably heard of this
we could talk about maybe putting a
temperature change on a sample
right but the temperature difference say
on a bridge
and you will notice that the expansion
joints in the bridge will either
close or open depending upon whether
it's cold or hot
it's really i should have said it the
other way they close when it's hot they
open when it's cold
but that temperature change results in
also a deformation of the sample a
change in length
for example which is a strain
and the thermal expansion coefficient
relates the two