i just want to say a word about the
theoretical density so where does this
theoretical density equation come from
and how does that compare to
experimental densities
so in your text you'll find an equation
for the
theoretical density okay where does this
come from this is really just a unit
conversion
so if you think about density which is
going to be some kind of a quantity
over a volume okay
unless we're talking about linear
densities or planar densities which are
quantity per length or quantity per area
here we've got a quantity per volume and
we normally think of
something like grams per centimeter
cubed
as our density that we could look up in
the textbook
but we could also have a density just
simply the number of atoms
say per volume that's the density
quantity right we got a total number of
atoms per
per volume so that's really kind of
where we start
and so in this equation here n is just
the number of atoms
in the unit cell and that takes into
account 1
8 for the corners one half for the faces
and then anything inside of the cell
would be counted as one
and so you'll you'll recall hopefully
that the body centered cubic
n is equal to two and for the face
centered cubic if we count those we'll
get n is equal to four
okay so that's the number of atoms per
unit cell and then all we need
is the volume of the unit cell which we
know
in the cubic system then is just that
edge length lattice parameter a
cubed so that will give us atoms per
volume
now if we want to convert that into a
grams per
centimeter cubed term then what we need
to do
is take the atomic weight which is
written in grams per mole
okay but we know atoms so let's rewrite
grams per mole
in terms of grams per atom and then we
can just multiply so we'll use
avogadro's
number of atoms in a mole that converts
to grams per atom
so now i know the number of atoms per
volume i know how many grams per atom
so if i just go ahead and multiply those
i'll get my grams per volume
which is the density that i'm used to
looking up and so that's that's all
the theoretical density is so
the theoretical density does assume that
these the crystal structures
that we're using right i'd assume that
we're dealing with
atoms as spheres uh hard spheres
and that actually works very well in
most cases
but there are times when the atoms don't
behave exactly like hard spheres
and in the hcp system the hexagonal
close pack system
we often will see that that the
the stretch in the c direction many
times is not
as large as it should be well
theoretically
experimentally it's smaller and that's
because in that c
direction instead of the atoms acting as
spheres
they get squashed so they're more like
ellipsoids
and so that c dimension is a little bit
smaller
than what is expected theoretically and
so the densities then
therefore be greater experimentally in
some of those cases it's not hugely
greater just a small
a small change but you will see that and
i think you have a
question perhaps in your homework on
that
but i know that it's in your reading
okay