all right welcome to part two
of chapter five diffusion in solids
we left off last time describing
the vacancy and interstitial mechanism
for diffusion
those are the mechanisms for how
diffusion occurs.  This time
we'd like to address why this is an
important part of processing
so the book goes through a couple of
examples we're going to just take a look
at two.
One of the things that the movement of
mass or diffusion
in a solid allows us to do is to case
harden the surface
so let's say for example we have a gear
that's made from
a relatively ductile steel
so that we don't end up with cracking.
Ductile materials tend to not be very
good in wear
and so we would like to harden the
surface increase its hardness
which will increase its wear properties
well if you increase the
carbon concentration in steel
it increases its hardness so what we
could do here is diffuse
carbon into the surface of the steel so
that we
create a case hardened
surface okay so it'll resist
wear but the ductility of the gear
itself
will resist fracture and failure okay so
this is called
case hardening this is interstitial
diffusion this particular case
of carbon in iron
so we will learn how to predict this
as we move on all right another case
is in the processing of
silicon so what we could do with silicon
is
we could dope phosphorus for n-type
semiconductors
in a pattern and so the
steps would be to deposit phosphorus
on the surface in a pattern of interest
heat it up right so the diffusion moves
quicker
and the phosphorus would then diffuse
into the silicon
resulting in a doped n-type
semiconductor
in some designed pattern
okay so next time in the next video
we're going to discuss how the rate of
diffusion can be predicted
for the very simple case of steady state
diffusion