recall that we talked about linear
elastic behavior before and we've talked
about hooke's law
the elastic modulus or young's modulus
and our definitions of stress and strain
so what we want to do today is to keep
going beyond this
region here which we get elastic
behavior
let's keep moving along and see what
happens as we get to higher and higher
stress values
all right so as we keep going at some
point we're going to get to what's
called the proportional limit
and this is the limit at which we no
longer have this
linear region where we define again as
the elastic modulus
but in fact we start to form
permanent or plastic deformation
so to the left of this point it's all
elastic
to the right of this point it's elastic
plus plastic plastic was elastic so
we're adding in
a plastic component but if we were to
unload in this region we would get back
the elastic piece for example to stop
here
and we were to unload this unloading
would follow the slope of the elastic
modulus
but notice we no longer return back to
zero but in fact we have an offset in
the string that's our permanent
deformation our permanent increase in
length
of our sample so
we also have this definition of the
healed strength so most of the time
what's given in problems and is
tabulated is the yield strength
not the proportional limit okay
so the yield strength is defined by
what's called a 0.2 percent
offset pool so the yield strength when
people say that they mean
0.2 offset yield strength okay but no
one says all of that
all right so this yield strength is
defined by
on the strain axis moving over to .002
and strain right point two percent
and at that point we go ahead and we
draw
[Music]
a line with the slope of the elastic
modulus
and then where that line hits our stress
strain curve that
is our yield strength value so that's
the method that we would use to find
that
so why do we use that and not the
proportional limit
well the problem with the proportional
limit is that it's difficult to really
define where that is
so this is very idealized data so it's
fairly easy to see
if we were to put a nice straight line
on the initial part we could see
where it starts to deviate and we could
define this point
but many times for real data
it's very difficult to define exactly
where this proportional limit is
okay so the point two percent works very
well
um in particular this is this is really
true for the the metals and alloys
we'll talk about the polymers when we
get to that chapter
and the ceramics will see that they
don't have
yield points they just fracture before
they
would actually ever get the plastic
deformation
okay so we use this method this point
two percent and although it makes it
look like there's quite a difference
between the
the proportional limit and the yield
strength
in reality there is not a big difference
between these two points
this curve is just really exaggerated
for the sake of defining
these two values so again this is the
one that we are going to stick with
the yield strings in some text this is
given sigma 0 sub 0
as the symbol instead of sigma sub y
our text it uses sigma sub y
but if you're looking at a mechanical
text you may see sigma zero
written instead okay all right
there are some uh stress strain curves
uh particularly in
or the plain carbon steels i should say
mainly just higher than carbon and
no additional elements
where the curve may actually continue on
up to some particular point so this is
all
elastic and then when the curve
deviates from this the stress actually
drops
and then we get this what's called
serrated yielding
and then the curve would then start
continuing on
um and behaving like like the rest of
most samples we'll take a look at that
apart in a minute
and if we do this point two percent
offset yield strength we'll see the draw
put us
in this lower yield point region
so this upper yield point is similar to
uh stick slip type friction cases
so the upper is kind of the stick and
then once
you finally surpass that your
sample will continue on your to move
say in the dynamic friction case
or in this case we're starting to move
dislocations
and once we get them moving
they move at a lower stress value so the
lower yield
point is the is the design point here
not the upper
all right so let's keep going beyond
that region so again here's the elastic
region
so somewhere and here's a proportional
limit um
if we do our offset yield strength
we will probably end up pretty much the
same place
on this scale of the curve for the yield
strength itself
we can keep going eventually we're going
to get to a maximum value this is
referred to as the
tensile strength or the ultimate
strength
sigma ultimate that's typically in
mechanics books
tensile strength is usually used in
materials books
and at that point the curve will start
to fall off and then eventually
we get fracture all right so
what's happening at the maximum here is
that this is the point at which the
diameter of the sample undergoes an
instability and starts to neck
and once it starts to neck and shrink in
this one location
then all of the strain the plastic
deformation gets confined in that region
and then
we eventually have a failure
i'll post this video in
in canvas for you and we can see this
copper rod being pulled
and then as it's going you'll see that
it next down and then eventually fails
hopefully you also saw that when you
watch the tensile video for the
stainless steel sample you saw that
necking behavior
and then eventually the failure
if we take a look at samples that have
failed in a tension test
you can see two main kinds of behaviors
here
one is where the cross-sectional area
the diameter here you can clearly see
has decreased right
and another case where it looks like
there's no change and we just have
a flat fracture this one that's
decreased also seems to have this
shear lip on it this kind of looks like
a cup
there's kind of the bottom of the cup in
the sheer lip and
this one is more like a cone it's a cup
and cone fracture
okay this is a shear fracture this is a
brittle fracture
shear fracture and a brittle fracture
so the ductal sample will have a lot of
change
in this cross-sectional area um go ahead
and take a look
at the full curve again and we'll just
point out
a couple of properties that we can get
off of this
so again this initial region we have the
full set of data we're going to have to
do is re-plot it
and we're going to need to replot that
so that we can actually measure
the slope here in this initial region
okay to get the elastic modulus that's
shown here
we're going to need to be able to see
this .002
to do our offset remember this is the
same slope
and then where it hits our curve that is
our yield strength
then we use the full curve to define the
tensile strength or ultimate strength of
the sample
and ultimately the strain
at fracture so this could be related to
the ductility the sample the percent
elongation
at fracture in this case being 37
all right this is says referred to here
as fake data this
means idealized schematic data i'm going
to show you a real
data in a next video
so again summary we can get the elastic
modulus
from that linear region we can get
the strength and there's two types
there's the yield strength
and then there's the ultimate strength
or tensile strength
okay so when one says the strength of
the sample you can already see
that you have to be careful because
there's two different types right the
yield strength here
defining when we go plastic and then
tensile strength
being that ultimate load the sample can
withstand before it starts necking and
final failure
the ductility can be defined in terms of
that percent elongation
at failure so we just saw a case for 37
percent
the ductility could also be measured in
terms of a percent
reduction in area okay so how much did
the sample change
in cross-sectional area
so that's a measure of ductility so we
can actually put some numbers to
ductility now
instead of just referring to a sample as
being a ductal or not
if we take a look at the material
properties
so we have here structure insensitive
this is the elastic modulus the density
of the sample
melting point so these things are are
all material properties and they're
relatively insensitive to any kind of
structural changes
so it doesn't matter how many
dislocations i have in my sample
for for example my elastic
properties will not change
so the yield strength
the tensile strength and things like
ductility these will
all change with the number of
dislocations in my sample
maybe the size of grains in my sample so
those would be structure sensitive
properties
there's still material properties