all right before watching this video
uh on mechanical behavior this is part
one
of chapter six you wanna go ahead and
watch the youtube video
that shows a pencil testing of a
stainless steel
sampling explains the use of an
extensometer
and how the stress strain curve is taken
that's in canvas for for your
convenience
all right just a reminder that in the
beginning of chapter six you will find
the
learning objectives and we will take a
look at all these learning objectives
throughout this chapter
the exception uh being true stress and
true stream
that is a little bit later in the
chapter so you don't have to worry about
this learning objective
we are going to be sticking with
engineering stress and engineering
strain which i'm going to go ahead and
define
all right so um we could talk about a
tension test or we could talk about a
compression test
and just the reverse of the applied
force so an attention test we're
we're pulling on the sample we're
stretching the sample and changing its
length
increasing its length and we would get
some
change in length delta l if we take a
look at the length minus the original
length
and if we were to take that delta l and
divide it by this original length
then we would have the definition here
of strain
okay so it's dimensionless it's a length
over a length
for compression that would be exactly
the same thing except delta l would end
up as a negative number and we would
have a negative strain value
the stress is defined as negative when
when it's in compression that's just
as a convention
and the stress is defined as that
applied force
divided by the initial cross-sectional
area and that would be in units of
pascals
shear stress and shear strain are
defined as the distortion
in the sample so if we have a cubic
block
say for example and we were to apply a
shear stress to the surface
this is kind of like having a deck of
cards and pulling on the bottom of the
deck and pushing on the top of the deck
you create a sheer
and it distorts the shape
of the original deck and so we would
define
that distortion that delta l for the
change in length
as defined in this figure over the
original length as our shear strain
that's also the tangent of the angle of
distortion
the shear stress is also defined as the
force divided by that original
area it's just now that that area is now
parallel
so in the deck of cards example the
force is applied to the face
of that top card and bottom card that
would be your original area