uh so last time we defined stress and
strain
we defined hooke's law linear elastic
non-linear elastic
and we defined the elastic modulus or
young's modulus
so this time what i'm going to do is
just kind of
go ahead and basically relate where this
elastic modulus comes from so in this
elastic region
it's important to note that we are we
are not displacing
uh rows of atoms or planes of atoms
relative to another plane
like we would in plastic deformation
we're simply stretching
bonds so you recall this
hopefully this energy
plot here as we have two atoms
approaching each other
and we said that the atoms will sit down
here in this well
at an equilibrium separation
r0
and the bond energy e0 so when we start
elastically stretching
we're going to be let's say if we're in
tension we're going to be increasing
this equilibrium position
or we're going to be displacing the
atoms out of their equilibrium positions
what i should say
and then again if we and so that would
be us
walking say along this curve i'm really
exaggerating
the amount that we would walk along that
curve here but we'll be walking along
this curve here
as we stretch the sample
and then if we let go we would come back
to this equilibrium position
so another way to kind of see that is to
go ahead and take the
derivative of this energy
with respect to the separation
atomic separation r okay
and this is proportional to a force
and so that's what we have up here on
this top curve we have the force
okay and so if we take a look at the
slope
down here at our equilibrium position
you can see the slope is zero
so on our force curve you can see if we
end up with a with zero here
so this equilibrium value we had in the
energy curve
the other way to think about it is that
that's the location where the sum of the
forces
is equal to zero all right so if that's
the case
then if we were to take a look at the
slope
in here at this equilibrium position
where the sum of the forces is zero
then we now have a slope that looks like
a force versus separation in other words
this slope here should be
proportional to
the elastic modulus i'm just going to
spell that out so you don't think that e
means energy here so the slope nail is
proportional to the elastomodulus
it looks like our stress strain curve
we'd have to go through some conversions
to actually
get the elastic value because we are in
units of force
and atomic separation so we would need
to
figure out how to come up with an area
to make that a stress
and in what way and how we would come
about making this a strain value
but what we can do is at least in a
relative sense we can understand how
when we have one material that's very
strongly bound
so in the energy this would be the case
for the
high gonna try and avoid e here too many
e's
i'll just write bond energy all right we
talked about bond energy
so the strongly bound case would be
where the bond energy is
high this one is is the case for the
bond energy being
low or at least lower than the red curve
here
so more shallower well from the energy
plot
and so if you take a look at those what
you will find is that these slopes
at the equilibrium positions is much
steeper for the
strongly bound sample as compared to the
weekly bound sample
and so we would expect the strongly
bound sample
to have the higher elastic modulus
right or young's modulus so that'll be a
high elastic modulus
this other one here then would have the
lower
elastic modulus so the modulus
is proportional to again the derivative
of the force with respect to r evaluated
at that equilibrium position