All right, for homework you will
be looking at the attractive and
repulsive energies between two ions. This
is this example we have potassium
and chloride. I don't remember I
thought my head with your homework
was but they will give you
the. Attractive equation, the repulsive
equation. And remember, again, what we
need is just the net. So we're just
simply going to plot, simply going to add
these two. We're going to do this in
a plot, so I'll show you what it
looks like in Excel. Um,
and then I'll post maybe a video helping
you actually work through Excel if you're
having trouble. But in Excel, we can go
ahead and make a column for the
attractive for repulsive and then add the
two and then plot all of those versus
the radius R and we'll generate this
curve that we just. Call and then from
there we can read off the bond energy
and the equilibriums atom spacing.
OK, so again, this is going to remind you
of the equation. This is the data that
was given and I have all of that written
over here from my constants.
In this case, I actually went through and
did the derivative of the equation and
found the equations for E0 and R0. So
that's what these were for. You don't
have to do that, these are calculated.
And So what I need to do is
just simply plot this equation. So what
I'm going to do is make a column
of R values and the units are in
nanometers. So I'll go ahead and redo
that. And then I'll make a column for
the attractive energy piece and a column
for the repulsive energy piece.
And then I'll go ahead and add those two
for the net energy. And then all I need
to do is select these columns and tell
Excel to go ahead and scatter plot it.
And I'll get something like this here on
the right. I know when you first go ahead
and do this in Excel, which you'll
probably find is that you don't see
actually anything. Except for maybe a
flat line, and then it looks like your
curve kind of does that. So if you
double check on the limits of the axis
here, you'll probably find that they're
very, very high so that you can't see
as well, which is only on the order
of in this case, say almost .5 I
mean. Almost -5 EV's and that's because
it very close spacings. The repulsive
part is very very large so you notice the
size of these numbers. So what you can do
is either skip some of those when you go
ahead and do your plotting or easier just
go ahead and double click on your Y axis
and change the scale. Is something much
more reasonable and you'll get yourcurve.