all right welcome back to
part five i believe uh we are on now
we're going to take a look at the
non-steady state diffusion case
so we're going to predict the
concentration
in a material under the conditions where
we no longer
have this linear concentration gradient
like we saw in fixed first law
so we're going to end up using what's
called fixed second law in this case
so if we take fick's first law
and we apply to it a conservation of
mass
which is that the concentration in time
is equal to
the negative of the gradient of the flux
with position
and charles is trying to explain what
that is here in this picture in a second
but if we go ahead and combine those
then we'll go ahead and we'll get
fixed second law so dc dt is equal to
the derivative
of j which is fixed first law so take
the derivative of that with respect to x
and so i'll get the second derivative
here of concentration with position
and we made the assumption that d did
not depend on position
so that was pulled out front okay and
that's not always the case but it'll be
the case for the problems that we're
looking at here
all right so let's see if we can kind of
get to this
mass balance equation a little bit so
let's say that this
is represents a concentration profile
through our solid
okay so we have some surface value the
concentration falls off in our solvent
and then eventually it plateaus to this
value c0
which is the initial value of the
concentration
okay so maybe this is a steels and it
already has carbon in it that's my c0
value
and i put it in an environment rich in
carbon so that
i can bring my surface up to some higher
value and harden it
and then i apply heat and time to allow
that carbon to start diffusing in
to my steel okay so initially
i don't have any of the new carbon in
and then later time t1 it's starting to
move in
t2 t3 i'm moving even further in
to my solid all right so let's just take
a look at this
t2 curve here and look at this one point
if i go ahead and just draw a little box
here around this
one point represented as here
i can ask so this represents a point in
my material
so at this particular position i've got
a flux coming
in to this piece of material
and i'll have a flux that's also leaving
this base of material
and what i want to do is see which one
of these fluxes is bigger
so if i just take a look at the slope
here right because fixed first law
says dc dx the slope's what's important
what i can find is that the slope is
steeper on this side
than it is on this side right see how
the slope is becoming
less and less steep and so my flux is
actually bigger coming
in than it is leaving
and the difference in these fluxes over
the time step
and it's coming in an area then gives me
a kilogram
and so that tells me how much my
concentration then in this volume
has to increase with whatever that time
step is
so my little volume element the
concentration goes up with my time step
and it goes up by the difference in the
flux
across this location so that's dj dx
so that's kind of the physical idea of
how that works
since the flux coming in is larger than
the one leaving
then ultimately the concentration goes
up in this little volume element
and so at a later time t my value is
going to be higher so i get up here to
my t3 curve
okay so that's the idea but anyway we
get fixed second law
and we would need to solve that second
order differential equation
for whatever the conditions were for the
particular diffusion case that we had
so let's say that we were diffusing
copper into a bar of aluminum so this is
an aluminum bar i have copper here
on the surface and i'm going to diffuse
it into this surface
and then diffuse it this way one
dimensionally down the bar
so my surface concentration cs of
copper is shown here in this plot
okay so that's my surface i could have
some initial value
so that's represented out here i had
infinity here
my copper hasn't reached that far so
that's just my initial
to continue this on
and then with time we're going to end up
with these profiles as i move
more and more copper into this material
so my initial and boundary conditions
are that at time equals zero
i have an initial value for all x
and then at time greater than zero i set
my surface
to some fixed value that's x equals zero
for the surface
and i still maintain my c zero value
when x is equal to infinity okay so that
just says over the time frame of
my problem i never reached the other
side
so this doesn't have to be an infinite
thickness it just needs to be
thick relative to my time frame
so if i was to go ahead and solve those
differential equations
i'd end up with this error function
solution
shown here and in fact this is a fairly
simple problem if we start moving the
boundary conditions initial conditions
away from this one we'll find that we
can't solve them anymore analytically
and then we'd have to move into
numerical solutions
but this one we can so this is referred
to as a semi-infinite diffusion problem
this error function is a function that
you'll find in excel
matlab or mathematica sometimes on your
calculator
this is the definition of it but you're
not going to have to
do that what we're going to do is
calculate this value in here
and then just find the error function
like we would find the sine or
cosine or anything else this is my
concentration profile as a function of
position and time
my initial value and this is my surface
concentration value
so if i'm given uh say a diffuse
diffusion coefficient
and i'm given a particular time that i'm
interested in maybe one hour
i could calculate then the concentration
as a function of position that's what
these curves are
all right um this error function is also
tabulated so here is actually tabulated
value
for it so if you were to find
this x over 2 square root dt value
and then we'll just call this z
that's the z here you can look up the z
value
and go across and there's your error
function so the other function you can
see goes from zero
to one so after about 2.8 you can just
call it one and it stays
at one
so let's take a look at a quick example
so here we've got a an iron
carbon or steel it has initially 0.28
percent carbon in it that's my c
zero uh surface concentration
is at one that's my cs
my time is 49.5 hours i need to put that
in seconds
and the concentration now it's telling
us it's 0.35
at a position x equals to 4. so they're
actually giving us this one
and they're giving us the position
so what they haven't given us in this
case is actually the diffusion
coefficient
so that we can solve for and it wants to
know what the temperature of it
is that this was carried out okay well
there's no temperature in this equation
but recall that the temperature is in
the equation for
this so once we find d
and then if we're given the
pre-exponential and the
uh that's d0 and we're given the
activation energy q
then we could find t
so here's my equations my knowns
i'll go ahead and plug in okay
and this particular case i don't know d
so i can't calculate this and then go to
my table
i have to use my table in reverse i know
these values right here
so i can bring that one over here and
that'll all be
0.8125 so my error function
z is equal to the 0.8125
so then i could go to my table or my
calculator
and solve for what z gives me this
so i might have to do a little
interpolation
and i'll get a z of 0.93 and then
remember
z is this term x over 2 square root dt
i can solve for d everything else is
given
i get 2.6 times 10 to the minus 11
meters squared per second
and then the last step which i don't
have one here
is if i go ahead and look in the table
in your text you'll see a value for the
activation energy and the
pre-exponential
for carbon in iron you can use that
with the equation for the diffuse for
the diffusion coefficient
and you could calculate what the
temperature has to be to give you this
value
all right that was a mouthful so just a
little summary for you
generally diffusion is faster for more
open crystal structures
so that means lower density materials
or another way of saying it is low
atomic packing factor
okay so you expect the fusion to be
faster say for a body centered cubic
versus a face centered cubic material if
everything else is equal
materials with weaker bonds allow things
to move around them
much quicker than a material saying with
very strong bonds
that don't allow distortion of the
lattice so easily
smaller atoms tend to diffuse faster
than larger ones this was one of the
mechanisms for
interstitial diffusing diffusion moving
faster than vacancy
and then of course lower versus density
has to do with how much space is
available
in the unit cell or atomic packing
factor