all right welcome to uh chapter five
diffusion in solids and today we
would like to address how diffusion
occurs
why it's important part of processing
how the rate of diffusion can be
predicted for some simple cases
and how the fusion depends on structure
and temperature
all right so first we want to make some
observations
so one of the things that we find is
that if we were to take
two different materials and bind them
together
so maybe this is a film
and deposit a different type of material
film on top and then we allow some time
to pass
and we were to heat this up especially
that will help the process
what we would find is that there is
inter diffusion
there is a movement of mass where the
gray atoms would move into the orange
and the orange would move into the gray
so we'd start to see that the interface
between them
becomes diffuse and this would continue
until we get
complete mixing so we we see that
that mass wants to move from high
concentration
to low concentration
now the other thing that we'll see is
that even if we were to use
one material and we were to go ahead and
radio tag some of the atoms in that
material
then and we were to wait some time and
measure the sample again what we would
find is that those atoms
have actually moved around in the sample
so what we're seeing here is what's
called self-diffusion
the main idea is that things are
constantly moving and
it doesn't depend on the fact that they
are different materials
so that concentration uh this difference
isn't what matters like things move
around even
when it's a single pure element
so our mechanism is going to need to
account for this
all right so what's missing in those
figures
well what's missing are point defects
vacancies in particular
so if i want to move mass around i need
somewhere for the atoms to be able to
move it
move into and we've seen that vacancies
are defects that are temperature
dependent
and so if i am to have a vacant
hole here in my lattice then any of the
neighboring atoms can simply move into
this space
okay and then that'll look as if the
vacancy has
shifted position any of those
neighboring atoms can then move into
that space
and then the vacancy looks like it's
shift position again and so this process
just keeps occurring
it's completely random and that random
process
results in a mixing and i'll show this
to you in a simple
kind of demonstration uh let's say a few
other things you want to say about this
this particular sketch makes it appear
as if any of these atoms would just fall
into the hole
there's no reason why this atom um
would stay here if it can move over into
this one in reality
this lattice is tighter and when there's
a vacancy here
this whole region will relax inward a
little bit
and so in order to move one of these
atoms into the hole
it will actually first have to kind of
push atoms out of the way
and so this means that there is an
energy barrier
for this process of diffusion okay
so we're going to get another arrhenius
equation like we saw
for the number of vacancies in this case
the radius equation is going to describe
the rate at which we get diffusion how
fast this process occurs
so let me go ahead and just show you
through a simple
model here that a random process will
result
in the movement of mass from one
material to another
so what we've got here is some material
in red and some material in blue
we've got some vacancies in the lattice
and what the computer simulation does is
it takes each vacancy
and it randomly decides that it moves up
down left to right and that's a
completely random process
and so you'll see that these vacancies
don't go very far
because it's not biased and so there's a
lot of repeating
so they're just hopping around randomly
and hopefully what you can start to see
is that there is some exchange here at
the interface we're starting to get some
blue moving to the red side
a little red moving over here to the
blue side
you can also see that this is a fairly
inefficient process so it takes a lot of
movement
ultimately a lot of vacancies to really
move things around
so if we run this simulation a little
longer and this one is the same
type of simulation we have more atoms
and in this one we're going to go ahead
and take slices of like every i think
hundred time steps or so
and so this will let us see longer times
and you can see now
the movement of the green and the red
into each other
and this is a concentration profile
across that sample
so you can see that interface spreading
out and becoming
more and more diffuse again completely
random process
and so that kind of explains our what
appears to be
the movement of mass from high
concentration
to low in terms of the red atoms
they would be at high concentration
moving to low into the green
all right so this process of vacancy
diffusion depends on the number of
vacancies that we have
so that's going to depend on temperature
and it depends on
the frequency of which atoms
actually hop into this space and that's
going to depend upon
the activation energy the barrier
for the diffusion process
now another mechanism of diffusion is
referred to as interstitial diffusion
here we're moving small atoms in a host
of larger atoms and we're moving the
atoms that exist in these interstitial
sites this might be carbon say
in iron and then this atom can now move
to any of the neighboring interstitial
sites
now at low concentrations which is
usually what we're talking about
all of the interstitial sites around
this one are open available
okay so this is one reason why
interstitial diffusion is faster than
vacancy diffusion
because this one already has its sites
available
where the vacancy diffusion mechanism
depends on the availability of a vacancy
the number that we have
all right now in this picture also it
looks as if this atom can just kind of
zip through here and in reality this
space is much smaller
these atoms are much closer and so these
guys have to actually move out of the
way before this one would be able to hop
into this site so there's an activation
barrier again
for this movement although it's smaller
than in the vacancy case
so the second reason that interstitial
diffusion
is faster than vacancy diffusion is
because typically small atoms
vibrate faster and move quicker
than larger atoms every time this atom
vibrates it's considered an attempt
at moving into one of its neighboring
sites
so if it's vibrating faster it's
attempting more often
and inevitably it'll get the right
conditions and then we'll hop
in to the next interstitial site
okay so that is the mechanisms
vacancy mechanism and interstitial
mechanism
and in the next video we're going to go
ahead and we're going to address
why we're even studying diffusion why is
this important
at all