uh in chapter 6 mechanical behavior
and we're going to look today at some
additional
elastic constants still
in the elastic region
of space so let me go ahead and first
correct this slide
this should say sigma
font got messed up here and called s so
again we're going to have a sample that
we've pulled on where
we're originally at l0 and we stretch it
to l here an attention test
okay so we know that we can define our
strain
in the direction of pull we're going to
now be more specific and call that the z
direction
so that axial strain is then again just
this change in length
over the original length
but when we do that the sample doesn't
maintain the same
volume most of the time the volume of
the sample overall will increase
somewhat
as we're stretching bonds but at the
same time that we're stretching in one
dimension
the sample will typically
shrink in the other dimensions
all right so if this was a rod then it
would be shrinking in the
radial direction all right so
we can also talk about a delta l
or delta w here we'll call call it width
so we can take again the final width
minus the original width over the
original width so
you can see it's the same definition
it's just now that this lateral now
strain is going to end up a negative
quantity if we're pulling in tension
if we're pushing compression then it
would grow and we'd end up with a
positive
lateral strain okay so this is my axial
strain
in the direction of pull and this is my
lateral strain in the lateral directions
and if we take the lateral strain value
and divide that by the axial strain
value
and then we're going to put a negative
sign out here that's going to cancel
with the negative signs in these
lateral strains so that we have a
positive quantity
this is referred to as the poisson's
ratio
and this symbol here is not a v but it's
actually the greek letter nu
so that's our poisson ratio
so here's a chart of the values for the
poissons ratio
as you can condense you again the sample
you can see again the cluster
into different classes of materials but
take a look at the
range of the poisson's ratio you can see
that it seems to have a limit of about
0.5
right and we do have some materials
dropping off here below 0.1
but really most of them seem to be you
know somewhere in this sort of 0.2 to
0.5 region
we could roughly
say that the metals are somewhere
at about 0.33 or a third
you can see the elastomers are very
close to 0.5 value
polymers around .4
so what's the significance of these
values
this .5 value is the case for
an incompressible
solid okay so this is
where the change in volume is
essentially zero
all right so ideally right at point five
the
amount that you stretch the sample the
one dimension
will get countered by the amount that
it's contracting laterally so that the
overall volume of the sample
does not change okay so a lot of
biomaterials fall into this category
and the and our last numbers do
and then as we get below that value the
volume is increasing so as we move this
way
delta v change in volume is greater than
zero
okay so we're not quite contracting as
much as we are
are stretching but you you can see from
this chart
you know this idea that metals are about
a third is not great
but you will see in almost all textbooks
if we don't have a
number for a metal or an alloy and we
just want a quick calculation
that people use a third all the time
we can see for the polymers though the
convention would be to use
0.4
and then if we go ahead and take a look
now at the shear modulus
the young's modulus and the poisson
ratio you can see that they're not
independent of each other if i know any
two then i can get to the third
so again this is for linear elastic
behavior
for isotropic materials
so this particular equation doesn't take
into account the anisotropy that might
come off if we were looking at a single
crystal
all right sorry about this this note
we're not using the ces software this
summer
so here's the value of the shear moduli
you'll see that they're not much
different
than the elastic moduli you can see that
from this equation let's say that nu was
something like a third
right then this would be e
over something like you know 2.6
and so we're we expect the shear moduli
to be
you know a factor of of two or three
different from the
elastic modulus but not orders of
magnitude different
and so they're fairly similar again the
materials
um group very nicely when we plot this
versus density