the elastic modulus
is dependent upon temperature and you
can see that here in this plot
we also can see that for metals we're
looking at
elastic modulus values of hundreds of
gigapascals
and then you know aluminum may be down
at
70 gigapascals or something like that
which is also typical for
classes
now we learned about isotropic and
anisotropic properties before
the elastic modulus is also
a anisotropic property
it's a property that does depend on
direction and so
for the cubic system we have a simple
equation here
that says that we can find the elastic
modulus
in a uvw direction right this is just a
shorthand for saying that we're going to
pull
on our sample right in some direction so
if we're pulling along a diagonal that
would be a 1
1 1 direction or if we pull on the face
it might be like a one
zero zero direction so we're going to
pull it along a uvw
direction and if we know what the
elastic modulus
value is in the one zero zero
and then the 1 1 1 and so these are
tabulated we could go ahead and predict
from this equation
the elastic modulus in any uvw direction
all right i'll talk about these alpha
beta gammas here in just a second
but the plot below is trying to show
this anisotropy effect
and so this plot here kind of represents
the
sample so imagine that this is aligned
with the
cubic unit cell and so if i was to
pull along a face right so that would be
pulling here on this front face and then
it would be out the back face the
length here from the center of this
image
to the surface represents
the magnitude of the elastic modulus so
this would be the smallest the lowest
value of the elastic modulus we have so
you can see it in color in terms of blue
and you can see it in terms of
the length from the center is not very
big in this case
say compared to pulling it along
a body diagonal right
in that case we're going from again the
center
all the way out to this surface so
that's the magnitude
you can see that's the the highest
magnitude we have in this figure that
would
represent the stiffest direction the
highest value of the elastic modulus
and so this kind of a plot is just
trying to show you
visually how much the
anisotropy is for given material
so if it was completely isotropic
then this would be a sphere so the
distance from the center to the sphere
surface would be everywhere the same
okay now let's talk about the alpha beta
gamma in case you need to get these
the alpha beta gamma are def are called
direction cosines
okay so they're defined as the cosine of
the
angle between the
uvw direction that you're pulling in
and one of our our axes our a b or c
axes so let's say that we're looking at
the
axis a which is one zero zero
this is the angle theta
and alpha is equal to
the cosine of theta and then
by dot product definition
right this is uvw
dotted with one zero zero so these are
the two vectors we have
and then that's over the magnitude of
uvw
and the magnitude of one zero zero which
of course is one
so if we're finding the alpha beta gamma
we just need to go ahead and perform
this dot product
and divide by the magnitude of the uvw
so hopefully you can guess that the beta
then would be the same equation except
that we would end up dotting with the
b direction right and the gamma
we would end up dotting with our c
direction
so hopefully you can so these would be
the magnitudes again
uvw
ugw all right
so you get the idea
and then the magnitude of these are
genji's one
all right so that's the beta and that's
the gamma
all right
so there's a nice plot of the change in
the young's modulus for a variety of
materials
as a function of the density of the
plotting things against the density is a
real nice way of separating out a lot of
materials
in terms of their their families and
then these are also color coded
by uh the types of materials and you can
see that materials tend to cluster
so for example our you know our metals
and alloys are clustered
up here in this region are technical
ceramics
versus non-technical ceramics cluster a
little bit differently
so the non-technical might be glasses
technical might be
some kind of a titanium
oxide or zirconium based material for
example
polymers you can see that they are
clustering here
and then we've got elastomers those are
our rubbers
and as we move into the polymers chapter
which is going to be a
ways until we get there we'll see that
elastomers
are also polymers these are really
polymers but many times we'll separate
them out
just because they do behave so
differently from the general class of
polymers
all right and then we've got our foams
natural materials etc again so values
you're looking at
hundreds of right gigapascals up here
and then when you get to the polymers
you're looking at
something like gigapascal and elastomers
you're looking at what maybe 10
megapascals or so
all right so that is
it for this particular video and then
next time we're going to do is we're
going to go ahead and look at
some of the elastic constants
that we can define beyond just the
elastic modulus