going to go ahead and take a look at the
hardness test
now the hardness test is a relatively
simple and straightforward instrument
we basically take a tip of some type a
hard tip
this could be a sphere
it could be a pointed diamond shaped
there's various kinds of hardness tests
and the the sphere
or the tip of this machine could be made
out of various materials diamond
being in a lot of the more modern
instruments
and the basic idea is you take the
sample
and you would load it up to a specified
load under the machine
and then after doing so you would go
back and you would measure
the diameter of the hole that is left
behind on the sample
and so these two samples here if we were
to just compare
their images we could say that the
hardness
of this is brunel as rock one
if we compare these two samples we could
say the hardness
of this you know sample a here
is going to be less than the hardness of
this
sample b and we can tell that from the
size of the indent
so there's a much larger indent here
in the sample a as compared to b you can
also start to see in in sample a around
the edges of this indent that you're
starting to get a little pile up you can
see sort of the plastic deformation
if you were to apply a much smaller load
and a smaller tip you can get much
smaller indentations
but for these two samples they're really
too small to accurately measure
so that's the basic idea of the hardness
test it's relatively straightforward
it's relatively quick as a test
so there's a lot of different ones
there's the brunel hardness
which uses steel or tungsten carbide
spheres
and this is showing you the
the sphere that's used and then the hole
that's
left behind the diameter of the hole
that's left behind
so i guess to be consistent i should
have used a lowercase d in my
my last slide but then you go ahead and
you calculate this
bernal hardness value by simply taking
the load
and plugging in the values of the
indenter size
in the hole that was left behind the
vickers case so similar idea except now
it's got a diamond
uh pure middle tip you can see it's a
four-sided diamond
again you're going to go ahead and take
a look at the hole that's left behind
and you're looking at the diameter of
this hole
the new hardness this one is designed
for samples that sometimes are too
brittle for the vickers and where the
vickers might crack the sample
the nuke is a similar type but now it's
got this long axis
and so this allows you to measure
at least this long axis as a hole on the
surface
and you don't need to go as deep in
order to be able to
just accurately see what you might with
the vickers
and so it's got also its own hardness
equation here
and then rockwell can use diamond cones
or steel spheres
and it has various standard loads that
is
that are used and in the rockwell case
you're looking at the depth
of the indenter and i believe if you go
ahead and take a look at the
video that's posted in canvas on
hardness it'll walk you through
this rockwell case
so there is a the scale for these
different hardness values you can
convert from one scale to another and
some of these tests um
cover a much greater range of hardness
values
than other tests
so here's some new partners values just
for comparison
diamond of course is our hardest
material that we have
that's why it's used as the indenter tip
in many cases
7000 on the new partner scale
and to go on down to something we're
familiar with like a window type glass
we're looking at a hardness of about
550.
and then you're in the 2000 ranges for
the carbides tungsten carbide silicon
carbide
boron carbide aluminum oxide
and these are usually materials used in
a lot of cases for for grinding
applications
so the value of the hardness test is
that it's quick
and it's easy most of these instruments
are
portable so this means that you could
put one of these instruments on a
production line
and then as a sheet or some other
material that you're
producing comes through you could just
place a small indent in the corner
in that sense it's non-destructive and
you can get a quick measurement for
hardness
and that's a quality check if the
hardness changes then you know you've
got a quality control problem
the other advantage of this is also that
the hardness can be
correlated with the tensile strength and
the yield strength but here we've got
the case for the tensile strength
showing that if you were to do a
grinnell hardness test
and these are the units that the bernal
hardness test comes out
as kilograms per millimeter squared
and you multiply that by 3.45 you get
tensile strength a pretty good measure
of the tensile strength
of that material now this holds very
well for the steels that's where it's
originally developed
although a lot of people use that number
kind of blindly across
different materials you really shouldn't
and
you can see here that depending upon
whether you're looking at a brass
or a cast iron there are different
slopes different relationships here
so but once that relationship's known
then you have a nice way of doing a
quick test that you can correlate to
tensile strength
because otherwise you've got to take
your material that you're producing
you've got to cut out a
sample maybe a dog bone specimen you've
got to take it to get the instron
machine
and you know mount it in the grips and
run the test
it's a very you know it takes a more
time it's very time consuming
where this hardness test is quick may
take just a few seconds
all right