chapter three structure of crystalline
solids
so today we're going to take a look at
the structure
last time we took a look at the atomic
structure otherwise the bonding
between atoms we talked about primary
bond types
hopefully you can name three and we
talked about secondary bond types
today we're going to talk about the
atomic arrangement
of atoms how do the atoms pack to form a
crystal structure
the reason we're interested in
structures that structure directly
affects
properties and then ultimately we're
going to see
as we move through the course many
different ways of processing a material
and the processing ultimately will
affect structure
so ultimately affect properties
so understanding the structure property
relationship
and how processing affects structure
would help us tailor materials for
specific uses
so you can you can grow your own crystal
structures if you want alums a good
system to grow those are
very nice big crystals and these are an
alum that's just a spice
in your grocery store one of the things
you notice when you grow a single
crystal
and say this piece here is a single
right there's another one each of these
is a single crystal
so all the atoms in these different
pieces have the same structure and
they're all oriented the same way
one of the things you'll notice is that
their angles here
will show up and repeat in the different
structures
so the lengths of edges might change in
length but the angles are always the
same
so that implies there's some order to
the arrangement of the atoms
the two types that we're going to look
at is what's called face centered cubic
and body centered cubic that's where
we're going to focus this class
and you can see many of the common
metals have one of these two types of
structures
we're also going to talk just very
briefly about the hexagonal close pack
system
but we're going to focus all of our
calculations
on the face centered fcc or bcc
body centered so let's first take a look
at the face centered cubic
as you can see the face centered cubic
structure
first it's a cube cubic so we've got
atoms
forming the cube here
if i look at the positions of the atom's
centers
and then at the face of each cube
you have an atom so face centered cubic
there's another view of that and this is
showing you what the true unit cell is
that is the repeat unit and
it's showing you here now that we are
going indeed from the atom's centers
and so that's what's actually repeated
so if we continue
to add in more and more pieces we can
see that we build up
this face-centered cubic structure
all right so a couple of things we want
to know about when we're looking at the
structures
we want to know about how efficient the
atoms are packed into the structure
and how much of that is how much of this
unit cell is space
and how much of it is atom
and we want to know something about how
to find
the length of the cube edge
in terms of the radius
r of our atoms okay so first thing let's
go ahead and take a look at the number
of atoms per unit cell
okay we have listed here four and how do
we get that
so we've got if we take a look at our
cell up here you can see that we've got
a half of an atom
here at the face
okay and there are six faces
times one half of an atom for each face
center
so that's three atoms and then notice
that
the atoms on the corners are actually an
eighth of an atom
and there's eight corners
so that's one atom and so we have
four complete atom volumes
in one of our unit cells
so we've got four atoms
per area
cubed of our unit cell right
our volume of our unit cell is just
a cubed so let's find
a the edge length here so what we're
going to do to find a
is we want to take a look at our space
filling model again
and locate where the atoms are touching
so notice in the face centered system
the atoms
are touching along the face diagonals
and so what that tells me is that i've
got one
two three 4r
4 radii and relative to a
if i draw my right triangle here i got a
a and so that 4r there the hypotenuse
is then just a square root 2.
okay so that gives me that a is equal to
4r
over the square root 2. so it's just
another way of writing
to r square root 2. i'm going to leave
it in this 4r square root 2 format
because you see this will be
similar to what we see for the body
centered cubic structure
so i like this format a little better
all right so the atomic packing factor
here how well to be packed is just
simply the
volume of atoms
over the volume of the unit cell
okay so it's the fractional amount of
atom per total volume
we said the volume of atoms well one
atom
is four thirds pi
r cubed and we've got four atoms total
in the unit cell
the volume of our unit cell is a cubed
and a remember we already have it
written up here
a is equal to 4r square root of 2.
okay so i'm going to put that in for r
square root 2 cubed
all right so you just go ahead and
simplify these numbers the r's cancel
out
plug the rest of this in your calculator
and you're going to get 0.74
so in other words this is 74 atom
26 percent then is space
in this unit cell this is actually the
best that we can do and so this is
referred to as a close
packed structure
the body centered cubic structure again
we've got a cube
okay we always call the edge length a
but now we don't have atoms in the face
but we have an atom sitting here in the
body's center
so body centered cubic it's non-close
packed
it's building up my structure the atomic
packing factor now or the packing
efficiency is 68
there's now two atoms in this unit cell
and the edge length now is four r over
the square root of three
and i'm going to leave these for you
to drive yourself
and then this is the right triangle
that's going to help you with this
okay so edge length a
this is across the face so that's a
square root 2.
and then this is our body diagonal
and i guess i'll go ahead and give that
to you a square root of 3
right body diagonal cube