let's take a look at how to figure out
the
atom placement um on a specific plane
so we're going to go ahead in this case
and look at the atom placement
for the face center cubic structure on
the one
zero zero plane that's a face plane
it's the first thing to do is to figure
out where the plane is so
a one zero zero plane we kind of work in
reverse
and take the reciprocals
this will tell us the intercepts right
so if i take the reciprocal of one it's
one
and then remember these zeros then
correspond to
infinity so this means that it's
parallel
to the y direction parallel to the
z-direction
and it intersects the x-axis
at one right so that's this plane here
across the face
okay so that's the yz plane
all right so that's our our one zero
zero plane
and we like to use this sort of exploded
view
model because it's easier to see the
structure
where the planes are but we have to keep
in mind when we go ahead and
draw the atom placement
that we need to be looking at the actual
space filling model
right where the atoms are enlarged and
we see the atoms for example
are touching along the face diagonals
and that's very important
so i want to sketch that sort of view
okay so again if i go ahead and look at
the
1 0 0 plane or this particular case let
me go ahead and keep the
labeling that they've actually done here
this would be
a zero zero one plane
so let's talk about that a little bit
because that looks
a little confusing too because it looks
like this plane is
intercepting here at the origin
so whenever we do have a plane it goes
through the origin we always have to
shift it by one
unit cell direction we can shift it in
any direction that we want as long as
it's
by a unit cell vector so in this
particular case what i will do is we'll
take this plane and we'll go ahead and
shift it up
so that it's now located up here at the
top
okay now located up there at the top you
can see that the
intercept along the z-axis is one
and you can see that it's parallel now
to the x and y
axes and that's exactly what we have
here
as to 0 0 1 plane
so this applies any time it goes through
the origin
we're just going to need to shift shift
our plane
okay so we're taking a look though at
this bottom plane in terms of the
labeling and you can see now again
since we know they're touching along the
face diagonals
that when we sketch that we're going to
get this sketch here
and many times if you're if you if
you're sketching it yourselves
you know you can't draw a perfect square
that's certainly understandable what you
want to do is just go ahead and mark up
your sketch to let me know
for example that you drew a square so if
i go ahead and label
these two edges as a and i know that the
intent there is to make a square not a
rectangle
i also could draw in the directions that
the atoms are touching and you know
maybe just label
touching say along
face diagonals
now everything's clear and i know that
that was that was your intent
okay so that would be our zero zero one
plane
for the face-centered cubic
one other point you know we started this
off by saying we were going to sketch
the one zero
zero all of the phase planes in the
cubic system are identical
so it actually doesn't matter whether
we're sketching the 1
0 0 which is here the 0
0 1 which is the top
or the 0 1 0 which would be
this face out here those
all have the same geometry the same atom
placements in packing
and so we will sometimes refer to these
as a family of planes
since they're all identical and the
family of planes if you see it written
will look something like this with curly
braces but
i'm going to generally avoid that for
this class
all right what about the body centered
cubic let's go ahead and take a look at
the one
one zero plane for the body center cubic
so again this means that intercepts is
going to be one on the x
one on the y and then parallel
to the z so we'll go ahead and draw that
we've got an intercept of one
one right we call this our a
our b in our c
directions
and so i've got those two intercepts and
then since it's parallel to the z
then i know that my plane then looks
like this so that's the plane we're
going to sketch
um what do i see i've got atoms at the
corners
and i've got an atom right here in the
middle
right located at the one one-half
one-half one-half coordinate
and that one's also on this plane
so now to sketch this i'm going to have
to think again
about my space filling model
and realize that my atoms touch
along the body diagonal
okay and so in terms of this plane let
me
change my color for a second here
this means the atoms are touching right
along these body
a terrible line
along these body diagonals
and then from this one to this one
that's the plane that i want
to sketch
all right i know that's a bit of a mess
so here it is
with atoms labeled and now when you're
sketching a plane like this one notice
this is not the same as the one zero
zero that we sketch for the face
centered although it looks similar
but it's not square any long but a
rectangular
plane orientation so this is
a and our lattice parameter which would
be this
dimension here and then we've got
cutting across the face so this is
a square root 2. right so that's
this distance here is a square root 2.
so that would be my rectangular
placement of the atoms and so i do want
to label that
or if i'm on a test where it's multiple
choice and you see these sorts of labels
it's trying to tell you that this indeed
is supposed to be rectangular and it's
not square
so it's very important and then again
they're touching you can see here now
along these
body diagonals
okay so that's it good luck
see you next time