all right welcome to part three of
chapter four
defects and imperfections in crystalline
solids
we talked last time about the
two-dimensional
or line defects the only type of line
defect we have or dislocations
screw and edge okay they're related to
mechanical behavior
and then before that we looked at point
defects these are one-dimensional type
defects
maybe missing atoms or atoms in
locations between the host
atoms those are called interstices and
we can't refer to these as interstitial
sites
all right now we're going to see also
these point defects are going to be
related
to processing of materials i didn't
mention that before
so now we're going to go ahead and do
the interfacial or 3d defects
these are the highest energy defects
that we have
because now we're looking at large
collections of atoms across the surface
or between two grains or two phases
in a material
so what i've got here is a fairly old
image of a bubble raft again these
bubble wraps really work
well to show these kinds of concepts but
i have these
this bubble raft and when this bubble
raft
was developed again we've got the
uh hexagonal pattern here which
resembles
like a one one one surface and face
centered cubic
okay so we're just looking at a plane of
bubbles or
atoms refer to these as atoms now
and each of these regions where this
uh particular crystal structure is
occurring is a grain
or a crystal because this is a single
crystal i refer to them as greens now
when they're in a material
so there's a single crystal or green
there's another green another green at
the bottom
all right so if i was to sort of draw
lines here along
the the atoms in my material i can draw
lines
along the atoms here in this other grain
you can see the angle
difference between the two greens so
these two grains
are twisted relative to each other
and this is a fairly large angle of
difference and you can see that when
they come together
at the boundary there's a lot of
distortion
and a lot of extra space so this is all
the space
and distortion between these greens this
is a high angle boundary
so this particular boundary is going to
have the
higher energy as compared to the low
angle boundary that doesn't have
as much distortion again now this is
a 2d picture so this looks like a line
remember
this is occurring in 3d right these
grains here are in 3d and so
this is really an entire surface between
these grains
that we're talking about all right so
over here
you can see that the grain boundary
between these two
actually looks pretty good in spots
right
and you can see that the angle
difference between them is relatively
small
and so there's some agreement every so
often in fact
much of what is in here are basically
dislocations
so it ends up looking like kind of a row
of dislocations along this boundary to
make up for this
small misfit between these two grains
that's our low angle grain boundary and
it's going to have
lower energy than our high angle green
boundary
all right so i think this picture shows
it pretty nicely i think the one in your
textbook
uh is a little confusing because the low
angle boundary actually looks worse
than the high angle so think of this
kind of picture
now if we were to use a optical
microscope
and take a look at a surface after it's
been polished and etched
what the polishing and etching does is
polishing smoothens the surface
and then the etching attacks the
boundaries between the grains so it
actually eats the boundaries
and it does that because of the fact
that those boundaries have high energy
and so the corrosion or the etching due
to the
chemical that's put on here the acids
typically
are going to actually eat away at the
boundaries
so this is done relatively quickly not
for very long
just enough to put a groove in between
two
grains at the boundary then when you put
an optical microscope on it most of the
light reflects back nicely
but when it hits these boundaries it
reflects off and these will look dark
so here's a optical micrograph of an
iron chrome alloy
and anything i want you just to notice
here is the green boundaries
so this is referred to as a
polycrystalline sample
where it's got multiple crystals
and also called greens
so one of the things that we would like
to be able to do
is say something about the size of these
grains
so we could just measure diameter and
report that but what has been done is
something called a grain size number i
should
mention the reason why we want to put a
number on these
is that we will also find in the
strengthening chapter believe the
smaller they get
the higher strength the material has so
again this is a structure this on
the micro scale so we're looking at
grains
if we change their size they change the
mechanical behavior
of this particular material
so we'd like some way to characterize
the grain size number
this is g the grain size number varying
from 1 to 10
10 being very small grains so what you
do is basically take a
optical micrograph and then you count
the number of grains per inch squared so
you can physically
put an inch squared on the micrograph
count the number of grains in it
move your inch squared count again until
you get some a decent number for this
now we have it in the computer and of
course we can we can automate all of
this
but this is the way that it was done is
the way it was defined in our
optical micrograph that we would have
would be at 100x
so the grain size number is defined as
the greens
per inch squared 100x okay so
n here is the number of grains
per n squared at 100x we divide by the
log of two
add one and this gives us our green size
number
so many times what will happen is you'll
go ahead and count grains per inch
squared but your photograph
is at a different magnification so maybe
it was taken at 85x
but we still need this grain size number
and so we have to fix
the fact that our area that we're
looking at is different
if i have a lower magnification that i'm
going to be counting more grains than
should be there
right so the higher magnification i'm
i'm zooming into the sample
if you want and so an inch squared would
see
less grains so that's important for just
remembering
uh in terms of the correction which way
to go okay so i'm going to see a lower
number
so what i'm going to do is divide 85 by
and since this is an area not a linear
but an area
then i've got a square so my difference
would be the square
of 85 divided by 100. so i go ahead and
do that
multiply this 62.6 and it tells me i
should read
something like 45.2 grains for each
squared 100x
and then i can put that into my formula
and get my grain size number out at 6.5
all right so we got a way of
characterizing grain sizes
let's talk about different kinds of of
green boundaries so we
we talked about the high angle low angle
and then there's a special type called a
twin boundary
which has an even lower energy than the
low angle boundary
this twin boundary has a special
relationship
between the in the two grains in terms
of their
angle their angle of twist here
and so angle rotation so if you were to
take a crystal structure like this one
for example
this was the plane that was exposed you
can see that
if i match this special angle here
i can get there to be perfect alignment
along the grain boundary
they're all sharing this center atom the
distance from this corner
to that corner is the same so i'm
actually don't have any extra space here
now the symmetry is different i know
i'll have more like a kite
than i do a rectangle and so there is a
higher
energy here versus having no boundary at
all
but it's not bad and it's much lower
than the low angle boundary
so this is actually not a bubble raft up
here but this is a tm micrograph
at atomic resolution and you can see
this twin boundary here
and you can see these atoms and then the
slight
tilt off so this is like a mirror plane
if you want
these are mirrored these two if you were
to take an optical micrograph
something that has twins in it because
the
original grain let's take a look at say
this this is a grain boundary that's in
here
so these are all uh originally greens
and these greens
looks like maybe there's a line through
here or something these grains
were then distorted or stretched they
were deformed
a load was applied to them and they
resulted in a twinning
of the grain so these sharp lines here
represent part of the grain that was
that had undergone a a twin
a reorientation of the lattice
okay to accommodate the strain in the
structure
and so they usually show up as very
straight lines
and usually in pairs so you'll see like
here
there's a bad line here there's a twin
and then a pair and the reason they show
up in different contrast is that when
you
shift the grain like this you're by
moving it to a different angle and it
reflects the light
away from the camera and so it looks
dark and then
if you get it to twin back it will come
right back again
and so all of these straight lines you
see all throughout here
are all twin boundaries
so that's that's kind of neat you see
that a lot in face centered cubic
materials
all right that's our twin boundary
uh then we have the surface itself
so i can call this a lot of times we'll
call this the free surface
right but it's an interface it's an
interface between the solid and whatever
environment it's in
now this is the highest energy
so this is a higher energy than the high
angle grain boundary
think about it behind grain boundary
still has
atoms on the other side of the green
there's just a more open space
where the free surface now is missing
atoms altogether
so there's nothing out here but our
environment
this one's showing a complicated surface
just showing you that surfaces really
aren't just flat but there's actually
steps on them as we go from one plane
down to the parallel plane below it
the next parallel plane below that one
so you're kind of seeing that idea in
your textbook when you were reading
about
equivalent planes and these planes
these edges here or steps
might have missing atoms in them
so these are the kinks the atom could be
floating around on the surface by itself
it's an ad atom
uh you could have a hole in the terrace
so that's the vacancy it's just
on the surface okay this is a ledge
you don't need to worry about all of
this for our purposes
i mean the main thing we want to think
about is the fact that the surface
is a defect and it's higher than that
high energy grain boundary
so material really doesn't like to have
the surface
and in fact if we were to melt our
sample let's say this was a
sample of gold and we melted it it's
going to want to tend to form a ball
a sphere and that minimizes the total
surface area
all right the other thing we want to
know is that the
the surface that's exposed this plane
here
could be any of the planes in our
crystal this could be a one one one
surface
that could be a one zero zero surface
for example
and depending on what surface it is uh
what plane is showing
it will have a different energy and the
idea the basic idea here
concept is that the energy of the
surface
is related to the planar density of the
atoms
of this exposed plane so let me show you
that
picture form so let's say you have a
face centered cubic material
and i take a look at the structure of
two different kinds of planes
this is our one one one plane
and this one's actually a 1-1-0 plane
which your textbook has a
a sketch of this one i believe as well
so in this one the 1-1-1
plane here has definitely has the
highest density of packing right
the 110 plane you can see there's whole
missing rows of atoms
so when the planar when that density the
plane or density
all right is high as that
increases the energy
of this plane goes down i guess i wrote
that here for you
but uh so the one one one so the energy
of the one one one surface is less than
the energy
of the one one l okay
this is true for face centered cubic not
necessarily
body centered right there you'd have to
take a look at the planar density
also the planes you're interested in to
see which one would actually be the
lowest
all right so again though
even though there's different amounts of
surface energy
all of these planes would have a much
higher energy than a grain boundary okay
i'm sorry yes it's much higher energy
than green boundary i almost thought i
said that backwards
i just want to make you a quick chart in
terms of
energy so this would be
a low energy so it doesn't cost much
to form something on the low energy end
in fact if we get really low like a
vacancy
we actually even have an equilibrium
number of them
i didn't mention before that when we
talked about the vacancy that the reason
why you've got
equilibrium number is that vacancies add
disorder into the structure entropy
so we're lowering the energy of the
system
through entropy even though it costs
some energy to form the vacancies
right up it to some point and then it
costs more to form the vacancies
at which case we've reached the
equilibrium number
all right but i've got my my vacancy my
point defects
here and i really don't want to list all
the point defects
in a particular order because it depends
on the material
but so i'm going to just put point
defects here
so those are all my one-dimensional
types
then my next uh increase
in energy would be my my dislocation
these are my 2d or line defects
and then i get to the 3d or surface
defects
and here we've got the i'm going to put
these in order for you
the twin boundary then the low
angle grain boundary
the high angle grain boundary
and then the surface
and so far we saw that for the face
centered
we saw that the 1 1 1
had the lower energy than the
1 1 0 for example
so i could kind of separate those out if
i want
all right so that is the order of my
different energies
sometimes something like this shows up
on a test
and you're asked to
place an order the energy or compare the
energy of of
various defects okay just in terms of
which one's lower or higher not in terms
of actual values